Register of the David B. Abernethy papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Register of the David B. Abernethy papers
1946-1988
72051
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Correspondence, notes, reports, pamphlets, and other printed matter relating to political, economic, cultural, and social affairs in Nigeria and to the campus movement in the United States for divestment from South Africa.
Abernethy, David B.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1972. An increment was added in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
David B. Abernethy is Professor Emeritus of Political Science at Stanford University. Professor Abernethy received his B.A and Ph.D. degrees from Harvard University and his M.A. from Oxford University. Abernethy’s research focus is in sub-Saharan Africa and he is the author of The Political Dilemma of Popular Education: An African Case (Stanford, 1969) and The Dynamics of Global Dominance: European Overseas Empires, 1415-1980 (Yale, 2000).
Scope and Content of Collection
The David B. Abernethy papers contain notes, reports, correspondence, pamphlets, and other printed matter relating to political, economic, cultural and social affairs in Nigeria and to the campus movement in the United States for divestment from South Africa. The materials are divided into four series: Speeches and Writings, Correspondence, Subject File and Printed Matter.
The Speeches and Writings series covers field notes from Nigeria and divestment issues of South Africa. The rest of the collection includes correspondence, materials relating to education, labor movements, sports and tourism, and pamphlets and bulletins produced by various political, cultural, youth, women's, religious and economic groups. There are alos biographical sketches of prominent political leaders of 1960s Nigeria. The collection also includes congressional hearings on South Africa, reports by the Investment Responsibility Research Center and the South Africa Task Force, South African labor codes and press clippings that cover the economic and political issues of 1980s apartheid South Africa.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is organized into 4 series: Speeches and Writings, Correspondence, Subject File and Printed Matter.
Africa.; Nigeria.
- Speeches and Writings, 1964-1986
  Scope and Contents
  Composed of field notes from Nigeria, which cover such topics as teachers unions, questionnaires given to elementary and secondary Nigerian students, and Nigerian leaders. Also includes material on 1980s divestment issues in relation to South Africa.
  - Notes from field trip concerning Nigeria Union of Teachers. Notes: courtesy of General Secretary, E.E. Esua, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Notes of interviews with Nigerian leaders and citizens, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Notes, South Africa, 1979 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Questionnaire given to 1350 Southern Nigerian elementary and secondary students, 1964 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - “Stanford, the Corporations and South Africa: What Are Our Options?,”, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - “Statement before the Secretary of State’s Advisory Committee on South Africa,”, 1986 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Correspondence, 1973-1978
  - Adams, Rodney, 1976 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Arbuckle, Ernest, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Augsburger, Robert, 1976 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Caulfield, George T., 1976 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Crawford, Ralph J., Jr., 1978 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Irish, Paul, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Ogletree, Charles, 1974 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Rosenbaun, Lee, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Stone, Wilfred, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 15)
- Subject File, 1961-1985
  Includes biographical sketches of prominent 1960s Nigerian leaders, sports in Nigeria, facts about the country, higher education and pamphlets of major cities. The series also covers the topics of corporate, labor, investment, and divestment activities in apartheid South Africa.
  - Biographical Sketches of Nigerian Leaders, 1961-1985
    - Dr. Elizabeth Abimbola Awikuyi, undated (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Mbazulike Amechi, 1963 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Dr. Nnamdi Azikiwe, 1962 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Sir Abubakar Tafawa Balewa, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Sir Ahmadu Bello, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 20)
    - Dr. Taslim Olawale Elias, undated (Box-folder 1: 21)
    - Wazuri Ibrahim, undated (Box-folder 1: 22)
    - Dr. T. Adeoye Lambo, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 23)
    - Kingsley Ozuomba Mbadiwe, 1963 (Box-folder 1: 24)
    - Matthew Tawo Mbu, 1963 (Box-folder 1: 25)
    - Chief Dennis Osablebay (Box-folder 1: 26)
    - Muhammadu Inuwa Wada, 1962 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - “Background Information: The National Library of Nigeria,”, 1962 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - “Challenge New Investment in South Africa” by American Committee on Africa, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - “Church Project on United States Investments in Southern Africa - 1975," (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - “Code of Conduct for Companies with Subsidiaries, Branches or Representations in South Africa,", undated (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - “Corporate Activities in Namibia (South West Africa),", 1976 (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - “Corporate Activity in South Africa,” by Investment Responsibility Research Center, 1976 (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - “Essential Foundations for Non-discriminatory Business Practices and Codes of Investment in South Africa,”, undated (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Fact Sheet on Nigeria, 1963
    - Community Development in Nigeria, 1963 (Box-folder 1: 35)
    - The Economy of Nigeria, 1963 (Box-folder 1: 36)
    - The Government of Nigeria, 1963 (Box-folder 1: 37)
    - Nigerian Institutions of Higher Learning, 1963 (Box-folder 1: 38)
    - "Sports in Nigeria,", 1963 (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - “Facts about Nigeria: 8 Hints for Visitors,", 1961 (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - “How Institutions Voted on Shareholder Resolutions in the 1982 Proxy Season,” by Investor Responsibility Research Center, 1980 (Box-folder 1: 41)
  - "A Hundred Facts about Nigeria,", 1963 (Box-folder 1: 42)
  - “The Internationalization of Apartheid: The Role of the United States,", 1985 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "Labor Practices of U.S. Corporations in South Afirca," by Investor Responsibility Research Center, 1976 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - "Lagos,", undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - "Looking at Lagos,", undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - “On the Withdrawal of U.S. Corporate Interests from South Africa,” by South Africa Task Force, 1979 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - “Petition of Representatives of the Catholic Mothers of Eastern Nigeria to the Premier of Eastern Nigeria,”, undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - “Republican Nigeria,", undated (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - “A Responsible Investment Policy?” by R.G. Hamerton-Kelly, 1978 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - “Second Report on the Signatory Companies to the Sullivan Principles,", 1979 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - South African Task Force, 1979 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - “Southern Africa Perspectives: Voices for Disengagement,", undated (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - This is Nigeria, 1961-1973
    - Abeokuta, 1963 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - Benin, 1962 (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - Enugu, 1963 (Box-folder 2: 14)
    - Ibadan, 1963 (Box-folder 2: 15)
    - Kaduna, 1963 (Box-folder 2: 16)
    - Port Harcourt, 1963 (Box-folder 2: 17)
    - Sapele, 1963 (Box-folder 2: 18)
    - Zaria, 1963 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - "U.S. Corporations Support for Apartheid - IBM and Oil Companies," testimony before U.S. Senat eCommittee on Foreign Relations by Jennifer Davis, 1976 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - "Visiting Nigeria,", 1961 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - "Visitors to Nigeria,", 1961 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - "The Withdrawal Debate: U.S. Corporations and South Africa,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 23)
- Printed Matter, 1946-1988
  Includes pamphlets and bulletins produced by various political, cultural, youth, women's, religious, economic, and educational groups of 1960s Nigeria. Also includes press clippings that deal with economic and political issues of apartheid South Africa.
  - "Action Group Constitution,", undated (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - "African Unity," by Action Group, 1961 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - "Bilingualism in Eastern Region of Nigeria," by J.B.C. Etuak Okala, undated (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - “The Bishop’s Joint Circular on Education: Catholic Bishops of Nigeria,", undated (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - “The Book of Documents Vol. I,” by T. K. Utchay, 1957 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - “Bulletin No. 5: Notes on Paragraph 1(a) of Page 61 of the Nwosu Report,” by T.K. Utchay, 1958 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - “A Catholic View of Education” by the Catholic Hierarchy of Eastern Nigeria, 1964 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - “Code of Conduct for Companies with Interests in South Africa,", 1978 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - “Construction of Western Nigeria,”, 1963 (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - “The Council” Vol. 2. Journal of Western Nigeria Union of Local Authorities, 1963 (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - “Courage, Fathers Do Not Stumble,” by Chief S.L. Akintola, Premier, Western Nigeria, undated (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - “Crusade for Freedom,” by Eyo Ita, 1949 (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - “A Decade of National Education Movement,” by Eyo Ita, 1949 (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - “Democratic Socialism: Being the Manifesto of the Action Group for an Independent Nigeria,” by Action Group, 1960 (Box-folder 2: 37)
  - “The Eastern Nigeria Premier on Education,” by E. N. Ukpaby, undated (Box-folder 2: 38)
  - “Education Mission Bulletin: No. 1 and No. 2 on the Nwosu Committee Report,” by T. K. Utchay, 1958 (Box-folder 2: 39)
  - “The Emergence of Nationalism and Federalism in Nigeria,” by Akande Tugbiyele, 1956 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - “Facts about Eastern Nigeria Catholic Council (E.N.C.C.) Onitsha Archdiocese," by A. N. Okono, 1964 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - “For the Welfare of Us All,” manifesto of the Action Group of the Eastern Region General Election, 1957 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - “Forward with UPGA to Unity and Progress,” manifesto of United Progressive Grand Alliance (UPGA), 1964 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - “Government’s Reply to the Arochuku People” by Education Missionary Society, 1946-1950 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - “Grant’s Sketch of Calabar,” by Donald C. Simmons, 1958 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - “Heralds of Dawn,” by Eyo Ita, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - “Holman’s Voyage to Old Calabar,” by Donald C. Simmons, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - “How to Start a Company,” by the Boys Brigade of Nigeria, undated (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - “Ilara,” by Information Division, Ministry of Home Affairs, Ibadan, undated (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - “An Invitation for Co-operation to the Chief Inspector of Education. Eastern Region, Enugu," by T. K. Utchay, 1958 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - “It Is Now for You! A Call for Solidarity Efforts for Cunardia School, Port Harcourt,” by T. K. Utchay, 1961 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - “Legislators of Eastern Nigeria,”, 1958 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - “Legislative Instruments Made by the Administrator for Western Nigeria,”, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - “A Letter to the Eastern House of Assembly,” by T.K. Utchay, 1951 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - “A Letter to the Elders of Arochuku through His Highness Paramount Chief Kanu Oji, Oror, Arochuku,” by T. K. Utchay, 1951 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - “The Manifesto of the Socialist Workers and Farmers Party of Nigeria,”, undated (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - “A Manual on Action Group Party Organization,” by S. T. Oredein, undated (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - “Mass Education and the Citizen,” by J. S. Ogunlesi, 1959 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - “A Message to the Honourable Members with Copy to the Common Man,” by T. K. Utchay, 1950 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - “Methodist Church of Nigeria Foundation Conference,”, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - “Mid-Westerners! Vote Yes and Be Free,” by His Holiness Ovedje Erumagborie III, 1963 (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - “Minutes of First Working Conference," by the Methodist Church, Nigeria,”, 1963 (Box-folder 3: 23)
  - “Missionary Photographs No. 1,” by Education Missionary Society, Nigeria, undated (Box-folder 3: 24)
  - “My Appeal to the Premier of Eastern Region,” by T. K. Utchay, 1957 (Box-folder 3: 25)
  - “My Complaint to the Resident,” by T. K. Utchay, 1946 (Box-folder 3: 26)
  - “My Defence in 1946,” by T. K. Utchay, 1950 (Box-folder 3: 27)
  - “My Plan for Africa,” by Dr. Nnamdi Azikiwe, undated (Box-folder 3: 28)
  - “National Youth Renaissance,” by Eyo Ita, undated (Box-folder 3: 29)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 3: 30)
  - Newspaper clippings, “Wells Fargo’s Loan to South Africa,”, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 3: 31)
  - “Nigeria Church Union Committee: Relationship with Missionary Societies,”, 1964 (Box-folder 3: 32)
  - “Nigeria: Facts and Places,”, 1963 (Box-folder 3: 33)
  - “Nigeria Youth League Movement: A Resume of Programmes,” by Eyo Ita, undated (Box-folder 3: 34)
  - “Nigerian National Hymns and Prayers,” by J. N. B. Ebutcheh, undated (Box-folder 3: 35)
  - “Northern Elements Progressive Union (NEPU) Nepu’sawaba Manifesto,”, undated (Box-folder 3: 36)
  - “Ogbomosho,” by Information Division, Ministry of Home Affairs, Ibadan, undated (Box-folder 3: 37)
  - “One-Sided Argument: An Education Mission Booklet,” by Dinah Stock, 1950 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - “Operation Reconstruction in Western Nigeria,”, 1963 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - “Our Grammar School Must Go,” by Tai Solaria, 1963 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - “Patriotism on Trial: Being the Presidential Address Delivered by Chief T. E. A. Salubi, President-General to the General Council,", 1963 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - “The People’s Budget: A Nigerian Budget for Nigerians by a Nigerian,”, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - “Philosophy for Independent Nigeria,” by Chief Obafemi Awolowo, 1961 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - “The Present-Day Prophets and the Principles Upon Which They Wrote,” by J. Ade Aina, 1964 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - “Presidential Address by Dr. M. I. Okpara: Premier of Eastern Nigeria,”, 1964 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - “Presidential Address to Eastern Nigeria Catholic Council (E.N.C.C.),” by J. M. Nwosu, 1962 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Press clippings, South Africa, 1979 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - “Protests in Cunardia School, Port Harcourt,” by T. K. Utchay, 1960 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - “Reference Section: Catering Rest Houses and Hotels,”, 1962 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - “Report on the General Election to the Eastern House of Assembly,”, 1957 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - “Revolutions of Our Time: A National Day Message by Chief T. E .A. Salubi, Resident-General Urhobo Progress Union,”, 1962 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - “The Revolt of the Liberal Spirit in Nigeria,” by Eyo Ita, 1949 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - “Sapelle,” by Information Division, Ministry of Home Affairs, Ibadan, undated (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - “Six Months of Reconstruction in Western Nigeria,”, 1963 (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - “South Africa: Foreign Investment and Apartheid,” by Lawrence Litvak, Robert De Grasse and Kathleen McTigue, 1978 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - “South African Outlook: Labour Codes,”, 1979 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - “A Speech Delivered on the Occasion of the Laying of the Foundation of the Urhobo Progress Union (U.P.U.) National Secretariat at Warri by Chief T. E. A. Salubi, President-General of the Urhobo Progress Union,”, 1963 (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - “Speeches by the Administrator for Western Nigeria,” by Dr. M. A. Majekodunmi, 1962 (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - “Sterile Truths and Fertile Lies,” by Eyo Ita, 1949 (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - “Summer School Lectures,” by Action Group Bureau of Information, Ibadan, 1956 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - “The World Mental Health Calendar,” by Education Missionary Society, 1964 (Box-folder 4: 24)
  - “This Is Our Heritage: Presidential Address Delivered by Chief T. E. A. Salubi, President-General Urhobo Progress Union,”, 1962 (Box-folder 4: 25)
  - “Tomorrow’s Man,” by Information Division, Ministry of Home Affairs, Western Nigeria, 1959 (Box-folder 4: 26)
  - “Two Vital Fronts in Nigeria’s Advancement,” by Eyo Ita, 1949 (Box-folder 4: 27)
  - “United States Investment in South Africa,” by South Africa Catalyst Project, undated (Box-folder 4: 28)
  - “Western Nigeria: Quiz,”, undated (Box-folder 4: 29)
  - “Which Is More Important, English or Yoruba?” by W.R.L.C., 1954 (Box-folder 4: 30)
  - “Who Are the AROS?” by Gwilyn Iwan Jones, 1958 (Box-folder 4: 31)
  - “Zik’s Birthday Prayer,” by T. K. Utchay, 1959 (Box-folder 4: 32)